Okay, today's דף daf is דף ס' Daf Samech בבא מציעא Bava
Metzia 60. We pick up on the last line of the משנה
Mishnah on נ"ט עמוד ב' Nun Tet Amud Bet and מועדים לשמחה
Moadim Lesimcha and גוט ערב חג Gut Erev Chag and our learning
should be in the זכות zechut of the protection of the חיילים,
Chayalim, the חיילות Chayalot and the speedy end of the war and
return of the hostages and a cessation of all of the horrific
things that are happening on college campuses and the antisemitism, it should
just be a really a זמן גאולתנו zman geulatenu for all of
us. Okay, so we pick up with the next משנה. Mishnah. We've
been discussing אונאת ממון, Onaat Mamon, overcharging, and אונאת דברים, Onaat Devarim,
afflicting somebody with your words and now we return to issues relating
to sort of honesty in business. Not exactly overcharging, but issues about
honesty in business. אין מערבין פירות בפירות אפילו חדשים בחדשים: Ein me'arvin
perot be'ferot afilu chadashim be'chadashim: if you are selling the fruit of
a field, I'm selling you a bushel of my apples, you know,
or ten bushels of grain, you cannot mix into that grain that
you have or apples you have from a different field if the
person is intending to buy what exists from this field. Even if
it's new and new, even if they're of the same type of,
you know, age and therefore presumably the same type of quality. ואין
צריך לומר חדשים בישנים Ve'ein tzarich lomar chadashim be'yeshanim and you certainly
cannot mix up new with old. Old grain is presumably better because
it's more, it's more ready to be ground and to be made
into flour. So the new grain is of lesser quality or normally
would be less desirable or worth less value or worth less. באמת
אמרו ביין התירו לערב קשה ברך מפני שמשביחו. Be'emet amru be'yayin hitiru
l'areiv kasha berach מפני שמשביחו mipnei she'mashpicho. And in truth they said,
meaning and the גמרא Gemara will say באמת אמרו be'emet amru means
that this is the הלכה, Halacha, that with wine you're allowed to
mix up some hard wine with soft wine—I'm not exactly sure what
qualities that refers to, maybe more stronger wine and weaker wine—because adding
a little of the harsh wine into the soft wine improves it.
And as רש"י Rashi points out, therefore it would also be permissible
to add in some old grain with some new grain. You can
add in something that really is an improvement. But even if it's
of the same quality, the חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishnah is
you cannot mix from one field to the next if the person
is assuming that they're buying from a particular field. אין מערבין שמרי
יין ביין או נותן לו את שמריו: Ein me'arvin shimrei yayin be'yayin
o noten lo et shemarav: you cannot mix up the, you know,
the dross, the lees of the wine, you know, the goop at
the bottom, you cannot mix that up, but you can give him,
the person that you're selling it to, you can give him the
שמרים, shmarim, you can give him those lees. So what exactly that
means is not clear, we'll see about that in the
גמרא. Gemara. מי שנתערב מים ביינו לא ימכרנו בחנות אלא אם כן
הודיעו. Mi shenitarav mayim beyaino lo yimkerenu bechanut ella im ken hodio.
So as we know in the time of the גמרא, Gemara, they
would mix water with wine, sometimes a three-to-one ratio, sometimes a six-to-one
ratio, had to do with the fact that wine was their standard
drink, so it really made everything a type of, like, a wine
drink, everything became flavored.
People sometimes say that the wine was stronger in the time of
the גמרא, Gemara, but that's not really the reality. The reality is
that they needed something that was potable, something that was drinkable, and
straight water was not drinkable, so they mixed wine with water. Anyway,
okay, but normally when you would sell it, you would sell it
undiluted. Let's say
you
somehow accidentally mixed some water in your wine or you intentionally did
it, you planned to use it for yourself, you cannot now go
ahead and sell it in your store because people will assume that
the normal stuff they buy at the store is undiluted, unless you
inform the purchasers that you should know that this wine has already
been diluted. That obviously makes sense. All of this is about not
misrepresenting implicitly or explicitly. ולא לתגר אף על פי שהודיעו. Velo letagar
af al pi shehodio.
Now you also cannot sell it to a תגר, tager, to a
business person, meaning to somebody who is basically a wholesaler, buys the
wine and then sells it to the stores, because that type of
a person, you know, you're afraid that they will sell it to
the storekeepers and not tell the storekeepers that they are selling them
wine that has been diluted.
אלא אם כן הודיעו ולא לתגר אף על פי שהודיעו
שאינו אלא לרמות בו, Ella im ken hodio velo letagar af al
pi shehodio she'eino ela l'ramot bo,
because you know that he is only going to use it to
deceive, either to sell it to storekeepers without telling them or to
sell it in his own store without telling people. Now of course,
you know, you could then—why should you ever be able to sell
to any storekeeper or to any middleman? They can always mix in
wine and then turn around—mix in water and turn around and sell
it and pretend that it's undiluted. But obviously there's nothing you can
do about that, but giving them something that would be easy for
them, it's like too much of a temptation. You can't exactly say
it's לפני Lifnei either because it's not something that they need your
help to do to add some water to wine. But nevertheless, giving
them something that it's too easy of a temptation for them to
turn around and sell it without informing people, because in a way
you're also putting a burden on them to now inform people. They
might not have proactively decided to deceive, but now that they bought
wine from you, it's easier for them to just sell it to
the storekeepers or sell it to the customers without informing them. So
that you are not allowed to do
because you have to be concerned about what will result from it.
מקום שנהגו להטיל מים ביין יטילו. Makom shenahagu lehatil mayim beyayin yatilu.
Now if however it's standard to mix water with wine before it's
sold, then you can do it. Obviously then everybody knows what to
expect. התגר נוטל מה' גרנות ונותן לתוך מגורה אחת, מה' גיתות ונותן
לתוך פיטום אחד. Hatagar notel me-hei geranot venoten letok magura achat, me-hei
gitot venoten letok pitom echad.
So this again is this תגר Tagar is again a middleman and
a wholesaler, or I guess he's the one that whatever buys from
all of the people that are selling it in their field and
then he turns around and sells it to the stores. So even
though we said you cannot mix up grain from different fields, that's
when somebody is buying it direct from the farmer and is expecting
to get it all of the same field. But this person who's
the middleman, it's understood that he buys from many different farms, he
puts it all together and then he turns around and he sells
it to the store. So for him that is allowed and then
presumably it's also understood that when you're buying from the store you're
buying from stuff that's been collected and mixed from different fields. So
this middleman can take from five different granaries and put all into
his storage facility or from five different wine presses and put it
up in his vat and then go ahead and either sell it
directly to people or sell it to the stores. ובלבד שלא יהא
מתכוין לערב. Ubvilvad shelo yehei mitkaven l'arev.
Provided that he is not intentionally mixing. What does intention mixing? Obviously
he's intentionally mixing. But it means that he is not doing it
in a way to deceive. He's not basically buying all of his
stuff from one farm and then buying a small percentage from another
one and mixing it in and assuming that people won't know. If
this is doing it in a way that's intentionally misrepresenting
with the hope that people don't really understand what's going on, that's
not allowed. But if this is the normal way of doing business
and everybody understands it, that's okay. Okay, so let's take a look.
רש"י, Rashi, גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. Our rabbis taught. אין
צריך לומר חדשות מד' וישנות מג' דאין מערבין. Ein tzarich lomar chadashot
me-arba veyeshanot mishalosh d'ein me'arvin.
It goes without saying that if the new grain is selling four
for a dollar, four units for a dollar, and the old grain
is selling three units for a dollar, meaning the old grain is
more expensive because as we said it's easier to turn into flour,
that obviously you cannot mix up new grain with the old grain
and present it as old. דאין מערבין. De'ein me'arvin. אלא אפילו חדשות
מג' וישנות מד'. Ela afilu chadashot mishalosh veyeshanot me-arba.
But even if for some reason right now the new grain, maybe
this year was a better quality than last year, and the new
grain is actually goes three for a dollar and the old grain
goes four for a dollar, so the new grain is more expensive,
then you might think oh then I can mix up the new
grain with the old grain. No, even then you can't. אין מערבין
מפני שהאדם רוצה לשינן. Ein me'arvin mipnei she-adam rotze leyashnan. Because a
person would want to themselves make the new grain into old grain.
Meaning the way רש"י Rashi explains this is that the reason the
new grain is more expensive is not what I said that this
year was a better year than last year, but that sometimes people
want to buy the raw ingredients and make it old and themselves
be involved in the process of drying it out. So sometimes there
are things that might have a higher sale price, but it doesn't
mean in some objective way they're necessarily better and that you're improving
the mixture. And somebody who's buying old grain wants old grain, so
he doesn't care that people are willing to pay more for new
grain, he wants the old grain and you can't mix up the
new grain in the old grain. באמת אמרו ביין התירו לערב קשה
ברך מפני שמשביחו. Be-emet amru beyayin hiteiru le'arev kasheh berach mipnei she-mashbeecho.
By wine you can mix up the harsher one with the softer
one, it improves it. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, אדא אמרה,
ada amra, זאת אומרת, zot omeret, כל באמת אמרו הלכה היא. kol
be-emet amru halacha hi. This tells you,
זאת אומרת, zot omeret, that since they say in truth they said,
it's clear from the context that it's saying this is the הלכה.
Halacha. So whenever the משנה Mishnah says באמת אמרו Be-emet amru it's
telling you that this is the הלכה. Halacha. אמר רב נחמן, Amar
Rav Nachman, ובין הגיתות שנו. uvein hagitot shanu. When is this true
that you're allowed to mix up? When it's between the times of
the pressing. The way sort of רש"י Rashi explains it is that
when the wine hasn't like is still like bubbling a little bit
and when you mix the wines together, it actually their flavors blend.
But if it's at a time that the wine is already sort
of set... settled, you know, from the pressing, and then the flavors
won't blend well when you mix them, then it will not be
allowed. Okay.
So
that's during the time of the pressing, that's and the wine is
still fresh, that's when you're allowed to mix them. Okay. ואדנא דקא
מערבי שלא בין הגיתות V'idna d'ka maarvi shelo bein hagittot
but now when they people are actually the practice is to mix
wine even not during the time of the pressing, even after the
pressing period has been finished. אמר רב פפא דידעי וקא מחלי. Amar
Rav Papa d'yadei v'ka machli.
So people now they understand that that's what's done now, that this
stuff is mixed even at this less than ideal time and they're
okay with it. So again it all goes by expectation and norms.
ואיכא דאמרי הא מני רבי אחי היא דתניא רבי אחי מתיר בדבר
הנטעם. V'ika d'amri ha mani Rabbi Achi hi d'tanya Rabbi Achi matir
b'davar hanitam.
No,
this that you know that this fact that we allow it nowadays,
what is the practice nowadays about is that we allow people to
sell wine that's mixed even when it was not at the time
of the pressing. That follows the ruling of רבי אחי Rabbi Achi
who says that if you taste it before you buy it then
it's a certain like buyer beware. Then you know what you're tasting,
you know what you're buying, and therefore it's okay. So it's not
like we assume מוחל mochel because they're generally aware that this is
the practice but that actually people take it and therefore are making
a informed decision.
Okay. ואין מערבין שמרי יין ביין אבל נותן לו את שמריו. V'ein
maarvin shimrei yayin b'yayin aval noten lo et shmarav. You do not
mix up the lees of the wine with the wine but you
give it to them to the person. So what does this even
mean? The גמרא Gemara says והאמרת רישא אין מערבין כלל, V'ha'amarta reisha
ein maarvin klal, you don't mix it up? So what does it
mean if you can't mix it up and sell it with the
wine, people expect to be buying wine that's totally you know sifted
and doesn't have all that all that the grape goop in it?
So if they expect to be getting nice pure wine and you
can't include with it the lees, so what does it mean that
you can give it to them? So the גמרא Gemara says וכי
תימא מאי נותן לו את שמריו דקא מודע ליה? V'chi teima mai
noten lo et shmarav d'ka moda lei? Maybe it means you can
give it to him meaning you can inform him. You're allowed to
sell him wine mixed with the lees if you let him know.
נותן לו את שמריו Noten lo et shmarav means you can as
long as you can give it to him if you're explicit about
it, if that's how you want to read the משנה. Mishnah. המדקתני
סיפא לא ימכרנה בחנות אלא אם כן מודיעו,
Ha midektani seifa lo yimkarena
b'chanut ela im ken modio,
but no, the משנה Mishnah has a way of telling you that
it's okay when you inform. It says don't sell diluted wine in
the store unless you're informing the customer. ולא לתגר אף על פי
שמודיעו, V'lo l'tagar af al pi shemodio, but you can't sell it
to the to the person who's the salesman, either the middleman or
the store owner, even if you are going to inform him. What
you see from that משנה Mishnah about the diluted wine is that
when the משנה Mishnah wants to talk about the need to inform,
it says מודיעו. modio. So that can't be what's going on here
with the שמרים. shmarim. מכלל דרישא אף על גב דלא מודע ליה.
m'klal d'reisha af al gav d'la moda lei. So it sounds like
the case by the שמרים shmarim when it says you can give
him the שמרים shmarim is without informing him. So what does this
mean? What's the scenario we're describing? אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר, Amar
Rav Yehuda hachi ka'amar, here's what it means: אין מערבין שמרים של
אמש בשל יום ולא של יום בשל אמש אבל נותן לו את
שמריו. Ein maarvin shmarim shel emesh b'shel yom v'lo shel yom b'shel
emesh aval noten lo et shmarav.
What he is saying is that the key is מערבין שמרי יין
ביין. maarvin shimrei yayin b'yayin.
It's similar to the point before about מערבין הפירות. maarvin hapirot.
You cannot mix the lees of one wine with those of another.
You have two separate vats of wine pressings and so on, you
can't go ahead and one of them you poured off the wine
and you left the goop at the bottom and you can't go
ahead and mix it in with the other with the other wine.
A, you're giving you're adding more שמרים shmarim than existed, but B,
also the שמרים shmarim from a different wine are actually going to
negatively affect the taste. So the emphasis is on the word מערבין.
maarvin. You can't mix admix them from two different wines, but נותן
לו את שמריו noten lo et shmarav you can actually keep the
שמרים shmarim in the wine itself from the wine in which it
came. You can sell somebody like the orange juice with the pulp,
that is understood that that you know unless you're explicit otherwise that
you would get that wine comes together with the שמרים. shmarim. Okay.
אבל נותן לו את שמריו. Aval noten lo et shmarav. תניא נמי
הכי. Tanya nami hachi. ורבי יהודה אומר השופה יין לחברו הרי זה
לא יערב של אמש בשל יום. V'Rabbi Yehuda omer hashofeh yayin l'chavero
harei zeh lo yearev shel emesh b'shel yom. If you are pouring
wine like you know into שופה shofeh means like you're pouring it
gradually so that the lees sort of stay behind. So you're pouring
it, do not mix up today's wine with yesterday's wine and רש״י
Rashi really says it just really means any two different vats of
wine, any two different pressings of wine. ולא של יום בשל אמש
אבל של אמש בשל אמש ושל יום בשל יום. V'lo shel yom
b'shel emesh aval shel emesh b'shel emesh v'shel yom b'shel yom. All
right, so that's about the wine itself, that you can't mix different
wines even of different days because it'll affect the taste and similarly
you can't mix שמרים shmarim together together. But you can't mix it
with the wine itself. Okay. All right, now the גמרא Gemara goes
on, where are we? מי שנערב מים ביינו הרי זה
לא ימכרנו בחנות אלא אם כן הודיעו. Mi shenitrav mayim beyayno harei
ze lo yimkreno bechanut ela
im ken hodio. Now if you got some water mixed
up, then you're only allowed it diluted in your wine, you're only
allowed to sell it if you inform the customer, but you cannot
sell it to somebody who is not the direct customer because it's
giving them too much of a temptation. רבא אייתו ליה חמרא מחנותא.
Rava ayitu lei chamra mechanuta.
So they brought רבא Rava some wine from a store. מזגי, Mazgei,
and he mixed it up with water, you know, he diluted it,
which was the standard. טעמיה, Taamei, and he tasted it. לא הוי
בסים, Lo havi basim, he didn't like it. Okay, so he mixed
in the whole barrel, he mixed it up and he was not
happy with the taste and he wanted to return it after he'd
actually, you know, driven it off of the lot, after he'd actually
already mixed it with water. שדריה לחנותא, Shadrei lechanuta, he sent it
back to the store and apparently, you know, the store owner would
he had an arrangement with the store owner and you know, apparently
he was entitled to return it if he didn't like the taste.
But now we've got a problem because now the store owner is
getting diluted wine, and you're not allowed to give a store owner
diluted wine. אמר ליה אביי והנן תנן ולא לתגר אף על פי
שהודיעו. Amar lei Abaye vehanan tnan velo letagar af al pi shehodio.
You can't sell it to you can't sell it to a sales
to a person who's actually going to sell it as opposed to
an end user even if you inform them because then you're putting
the burden on them to inform the customer and they might not
bother. אמר ליה מזיגא דידי מידע ידיעא. Amar lei maziga didi meida
yadia.
Okay, now my mixing of water is known.
רש״י Rashi explains it means that he would very, very heavily dilute
his wine, so there's no possibility that anybody is going to be
deceived. As soon as somebody tastes it, it'll taste very diluted and
they'll know they'll know that this has been diluted with water. וכי
תימא דטפי ומחלי ליה ומזבין ליה. Vechi teima detafi umachlei lei umazbin
lei. Now you'll say oh okay, but so what? So now he's
got something that's heavily diluted. He'll add some more raw wine to
it and make it only slightly diluted and now he'll still be
able to deceive people. אם כן אין לדבר סוף. Im ken ein
ladavar sof. Okay, then there's no end to it. Then you shouldn't
even be able to sell raw wine because somebody could always deceive
if they want to deceive, right? So the problem here is not
that somebody who's going to go out of their way to deceive,
the problem is that you're giving them too much of an irresistible
temptation. You're actually making them obliging them to do something in order
to not deceive. Now they have to go out of their way
to inform somebody, they might not bother. But anything that would require
them to do an effort, we're not going to just סתם stam
be concerned that people are going to deceive. Okay. מקום שנהגו להטיל
מים ביין יטילו. Makom shenahagu lehatil mayim beyayin yatilu. If it's the
practice, you're allowed to do it. Everybody knows what to expect. תנא
למחצה לשליש ולרביע. Tana lemachetza leshlish uleravia.
So, you know, whatever is the standard dilution that people expect, half,
third, a quarter, that you do what is the standard. אמר רב
ובין הגיתות שנו. Amar Rav uvein hagitot shanu. And again we're talking
when it's during the time that the wine is being pressed, when
it's still very fresh and the dilution, you know, blends better with
the taste. Okay, and if that was the standard, then that's what
you're allowed to do, that's what people expect. Next משנה. Mishna. This
next משנה Mishna is a very important משנה Mishna in terms of
questions about fair and unfair competition. Let's take a look. רבי יהודה
אומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said: לא יחלק חנוני
קליות ואגוזים לתינוקות מפני שהוא מרגילן לבוא אצלו. Lo yachallek chenvani kaliyot
ve'egozim letinokot mipnei shehu margilan lavo etzlo.
So a storekeeper is not allowed to give out like, you know,
toasted grain and nuts to the kids because he's, you know, he's
he's enticing them. It's a you know, to come to his store,
and they're going to come take, you know, ask their parents, mommy,
mommy, let's go to this store, they give out free candy. So
that's unfair competition because it's not really that his prices are better
or the quality of his food is better. It's just that he's
got, you know, good advertisement and good and good come-ons. So that's
not fair. So to get people to come to your store, it's
not fair. Not that you're selling them something that's not worth its
value, but you're having people choose you over somebody else for not
something that's a real substantive reason of the value of what you're
selling. וחכמים מתירין. Vachachamim matirin. But the Sages permit
it, as we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, because, you know, the
other person can then offer other types of treats. So it's not
unfair competition. ולא יפחות את השער. Velo yifchot et hashaar. And you
cannot sell, you know, produce for less
than the going rate. You know, this is also this is like,
you know,
people stores that are able to, these big companies that are able
to undersell and sell at a loss in order to drive people
out of business. So here too, you know, this the first position
here presumably again of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is that if you're
you can't go ahead and sell under the going rate, it's not
fair to the other storekeepers.
וחכמים אומרים זכור לטוב. Vachachamim omrim zachur latov. he should be praised
for doing that because, you know, then that gets competition is good
for the consumer and it gets everybody to sell lower. זכור לטוב.
Zachur Latov.
Now again, this is not talking about a case where one person
has the means to actually sell even under cost,
and take a loss in order to drive somebody out of business.
This assumes presumably that it's relatively an equal playing field. There is
no greater discussion in the גמרא Gemara about how this might play
out for the חכמים Chachamim if it was an unequal playing field.
Okay. לא יבור את הגריסין דברי אבא שאול. Lo yavor et hagrisin
divrei Abba Shaul.
So אבא שאול Abba Shaul says you're not allowed to go ahead
and sift ground beans in order to sell the ones that look
good or, you know, sell them sifted for a higher price and
maybe even for a price that's even more than the added price
for the labor that was involved. Like the example I would think
about is, you know, if you go to the store and you
buy
thin cutlets. So you could obviously go ahead and, you know, buy
them in the normal way they are and pound them and thin
them yourself or even buy them, you know, on the bone and
take them off and do the whole thing yourself and but you're
paying for the service. Okay. So and even if in some objective
way the amount that it's improved that is less than the increased
price, that's a choice that you're going to make as a consumer
whether you're willing to pay for that convenience. So that's the issue
going on here.
So אבא שאול Abba Shaul does not allow it because he says
that you wind up paying more than that service of the, you
know, of the shelling of the grains or whatever is worth. וחכמים
מתירים, Vechachamim matirim, and the חכמים Chachamim allow it. ומודין שלא יבור
מעל פי המגורה שאינו אלא כגונב את העין. Umodin shelo yavor meal
pi hamigura sheino ela kegonev et haayin. But they of course even
the חכמים Chachamim agree that you can't have just the sifted grains
on the top, the sifted beans on the top and the, you
know, and the unshelled ones below it, because then somebody's going to
buy, they're going to think that they're going to get all sifted
stuff and they don't realize that that's just the top layer. That
obviously would be to deceive people, stealing the eye. אין מפרכסין לא
את האדם ולא את הבהמה ולא את הכלים. Ein mefarchasin lo et
haadam velo et habehema velo et hakelim. You're not allowed to like
make look, the גמרא Gemara is going to explain exactly what this
means, but essentially it means like ruddy up, you know, make look
healthy,
you know, or adorn whether
a person, if you're selling a slave, or an animal or any
type of object that you're selling, you can't do things to give
it a like a like a glow, you know, and that
is that makes it look newer or better than it actually is.
So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara and exactly what
some of the parameters of this are.
מאי טעמא דרבנן? Mai taama derabbanan? Why did the Rabbis say it's
okay for a storekeeper to give out nuts and and, you know,
and roasted grain or whatever? דאמר ליה אנא מפלגינא אמגוזי ואת פליג
שיסקי. Deamar lei ana mepalgina amgozei veat palig shiskei. Because the storekeeper
who's giving it out says, say look, I'm giving out nuts, you
go ahead and you give out candy. If you actually look at
רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says what's שיסקי? shiskei? Prunes. Okay. You can
give out your own stuff. So, you know, it's just good competition.
You're able to do it as well. Like I said, this does
not discuss what happens if it's really an unequal playing field. ולא
יפחות והחכמים זכור לטוב. Velo yifchot vehachachamim zachur latov. מאי טעמא דרבנן?
Mai taama derabbanan? Why did the Rabbis get not only it's permitted
but זכור לטוב, zachur latov, he should be remembered for good? So
משום mishum top of ס״ב Samech-Bet דקמרוח לתרעא, dekamravach letara, because
you go ahead, you like make easier, wider the market rate, meaning
that you lower the general going rate. If you start selling for
less, other people will start selling for less. Okay. ולא יבור יבור
את הגריסין, Velo yavor yavor et hagrisin, and you cannot go ahead
and sift out the like the beans, דברי
אבא שאול, divrei Abba Shaul, that's what אבא שאול Abba Shaul says.
And וחכמים מתירים, Vechachamim matirim, and the חכמים Chachamim allow it. מאן
חכמים? Man chachamim? Who are the חכמים? Chachamim? רבי אחא. Rabbi Acha.
דתניא רבי אחא מתיר בדבר הנראה. Detanya Rabbi Acha matir bedavar hanireh.
רבי אחא Rabbi Acha allows as long as you're able to see
what you're paying for. So if you look at רש״י, Rashi, top
line of רש״י, Rashi, הלא יכול הלוקח לראות ולהבין מה דמי הפסולת
הנבור מאלו שישנו באחרים וטוב לו להעלות בדמיהם של אלו יותר כדי
דמי הטורח. Halo yachol halokeach lirot ulehavin ma dmei hapsoles hanivrar meilu
sheyeshno beacherim vetov lo lehaalot bidmeihem shel eilu yoter kedei dmei hatorach.
Right. So רש״י Rashi says you're not just paying like to use
my example of the chicken breast, you're not
just paying
because, oh, you're not, it's more because of it doesn't have the
bone and that's why it's more. No, you're also paying for the
convenience. Somebody went to the problem of doing the sifting for you.
So אבא שאול Abba Shaul does not like it because he thinks
the only thing that you should be paying for is the fact
that you're getting, you're getting the
stuff itself and not the shells and the price is higher than
that. But the חכמים Chachamim are saying you know what you're getting
and you're paying for the convenience. Okay. Now גמרא, Gemara, אין מפרכסין
לא את האדם ולא את הכלים, Ein mefarchasin lo et haadam velo
et hakelim, you cannot beautify in a way that misrepresents like the...
things that you're selling. Okay, this is obviously a little uncomfortable because
it's talking also about selling slaves. תנו רבנן: Tano Rabbanan: אין משרביטין
את הבהמה, ein mesharvitin et habeheimah, you cannot go ahead and
like do
the hair of an animal to be
stiff to make it look I don't know ruddier or healthier or
fatter ואין נופחין בקרביים, ve'ein nofchin bekirbayim, you can't like blow up
if you're selling inner organs, you know, of an animal, you can't
blow them up to make them look take up more volume.
Of course this is done all the time, right, when people sell
a small amount of product in a big box. So all these
things about honesty in advertising.
Now, of course, they somewhere on the box it does say exactly
what the net weight is, but the size of the box is
very deceiving. So you know here some very similar type of concerns.
ואין שורין את הבשר במים, ve'ein shorin et habasar bamayim, you know
this is of course this seems clearly a problem. You cannot go
ahead and have the meat, if you're selling a steak let's say,
soak it in water so then it's going to look fatter or
even weigh more, that seems like you know a high degree of
deception there. מאי אין משרביטין? Mai ein mesharvitin?
So what's the phrase משרביטין? mesharvitin? Where does that what does that
mean? הכא תרגימו מיא דחיזרא. Hacha targimu maya dechizra.
Here in בבל Bavel they explained that that means water of a
Rashi says Rashi says what does חיזרא? chizra? Rashi says משקהו מי
סובין mashkehu mei subin
which is you know a type of what do you call it
like bran water. And that's something that would make the animal look
ruddier or healthier. ואיכא דאמרי רב כהנא מזקפיתא, Ve'icha de'amri Rav Kahana
mazkafita,
that he says no, it's a like it's a comb that you
comb that makes the hair stand up and again maybe you know
makes the flesh look better. שמואל שרא למימרמא תומיי לסרבלא. Shmuel shara
lemirmay tumei lesarvela.
Now Shmuel permitted so you know Shmuel permitted to sell like to
place fringes on a cloak, on a garment because there you're not
making the garment look better and misrepresenting its newness or anything, it
makes it more attractive and people want to buy it. Now again
the actual cost of the fringes, you know, might make the thing
look you know give the whole thing a better look and make
it more attractive than maybe the actual addition of the fringes is
worth, but nevertheless you're not misrepresenting anything. You're just making the whole
thing look better and more people would want to buy it. All
right, so Shmuel permitted that. רב יהודה שרא לכסחוכי כרמי. Rav Yehuda
shara lachaschuchi karmei.
Rav Yehuda permitted to like
you know clean colored garments, again make them look fresh. רבה שרא
למידק צראדין. Rabbah shara lemeidak tzaradin. Rabbah
permitted to like you know to like
cut or taper also types of
linen clothes. רבא שרא לצלומי גירי. Rava shara letzallumei girei. Rava permitted
to draw arrows on you know on clothes. רב פפא בר שמואל
שרא לצלומי דיקולי. Rav Pappa bar Shmuel shara letzallumei dikulei. And Rav
Pappa bar Shmuel allowed
to draw like ladders or baskets or whatever also on various clothes
or vessels. You know you could do things that make things look
pretty and then people are more their eyes are pulled to them
more and they're more attracted to them and they're more prepared to
buy them, but none of that is a misrepresenting of the thing
like it's newer or healthier you know than it actually is.
Okay, where were we? לצלומי גירי רב פפא בר שמואל שרא לצלומי
דיקולי. letzallumei girei Rav Pappa bar Shmuel shara letzallumei dikulei. I think
we just said that. והאנן תנן אין מפרכסין לא את האדם ולא
את הבהמה ולא את הכלים. Ve'hanan tenan ein mefarchasin lo et ha'adam
velo et habeheimah velo et hakeilim. So the Gemara says how is
this different than the point of the Mishnah, which you're not allowed
to do these things to make them look better? לא קשיא הא
בחדתי הא בעתיקי. Lo kashya ha bechadti ha be'atiki. It matters if
it's old or new. If it's old then you're doing things to
make them look new, that's misrepresenting. If it's new and you're doing
these things and you're adding a little fringe on it and a
little design to make it more attractive, then that's part of what
people pay for is that the thing is more attractive. Okay.
פירכוס דאדם מאי היא? Pirchus de'adam mai hi? So now what is
this beautifying that you would do for a person? You know we've
talked about an animal, we talked about vessels. What would it be
for a person? כי הא דההוא עבדא סבא דאזל צבעיה לרישיה ולדיקניה.
Ki ha de'hahu avda saba de'azal tzaveiyeh lereisheih uledikneih.
There was this old slave
who
went and he dyed his hair, he was you know he had
white hair and he dyed it black to make himself look young
and the hair of his head and of his beard. אתא לקמיה
דרבא ואמר ליה זבנן, Ata lekameih de'Rava ve'amar leih zavnan, buy me.
אמר ליה יהיו עניים בני ביתך. Amar leih yihiyu aniyim benei beitecha.
No,
we teach in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avos that you know the poor
should be in your household, so if I'm going to you know
bring people into my home and feed them. and supports them, the
way רש״י *Rashi* explains this, I mean you could say I'd rather
they be poor people, but רש״י *Rashi* says I'd rather they be
Jews. This was a non-Jew who was selling himself as a slave.
רש״י *Rashi* says there were no Jewish slaves at the time of
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, when there's no יובל *Yovel*. So I'd
rather if I'm going to be helping support people, I'd rather they
be poor people rather than a slave. אזל לקמיה דרב פפא בר
שמואל *Azal lekamei deRav Pappa bar Shmuel* he came to רב פפא
בר שמואל *Rav Pappa bar Shmuel*. זבניה רב פפא בר שמואל *Zavneia
Rav Pappa bar Shmuel* bought him and was deceived by the fact
that he had dyed his hair. יומא חד אמר ליה אשקין מיא
*Yoma chad amar lei ashkin maya*. So one day רב פפא *Rav
Pappa* said to the slave, go serve me water. אזל חוריה לרישיה
ולדיקניה *Azal chavrei le-reishei ule-dikneih*. He went and he whitened his head
and his beard, the hair on his head, like you know, he
removes the dye. אמר ליה חזי דאנא קשישנא מאבוך *Amar lei chazi
de-ana kashishna me-avuch*. Go look I'm older than your father, you know,
I'm too old you can't even ask me to go and do
something simple like get you water. Okay, you bought yourself a really
old slave and now you're going to have to support me and
I have very little value to you. קרי אנפשיה *Karei anafsheih* so
רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said about himself the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* צדיק
מצרה נחלץ ויבא אחר תחתיו *tzadik mi-tzara nechlatz ve-yavo acher tachtav* or
about also about רבא *Rava*. צדיק מצרה נחלץ ויבא אחר תחתיו *tzadik
mi-tzara nechlatz ve-yavo acher tachtav* or ויבא רשע תחתיו *ve-yavo rasha tachtav*
is actually what the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says.
A צדיק *tzadik* is saved from affliction, so רבא *Rava* was the
צדיק *tzadik* and he got saved from having to buy this person
that turned out to be an old slave and somebody else will
come and it actually says רשע *rasha* but you don't want to
call yourself a רשע *rasha*, somebody else will come and take his
place. I got stuck with this slave that רבא *Rava* wisely avoided.
הדרן עלך הזהב *Hadran alach ha-zahav*. That is the end of הזהב
*Ha-zahav*, the end of our discussion of אונאה *ona'ah* and fairness in
business. Now we turn to a very challenging פרק *perek*, איזהו נשך
neshech *Eizehu Neshech*, which is about the prohibition of charging interest. Let's
start and take a look. איזהו נשך neshech ואיזו תרבית tarbis *Eizehu
neshech ve-eizo tarbit*. What is נשך neshech *neshech* and תרבית tarbis *tarbit*?
The תורה Torah *Torah* says לא תקח מאתו נשך ותרבית neshech v'tarbis
*lo tikach me-ito neshech ve-tarbit*, right, do not when you lend money
do not take from somebody נשך neshech *neshech* and תרבית tarbis *tarbit*,
which means interest. And as we'll see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
they refer to different aspects of the interest. נשך neshech *neshech* is
like a bite, that from you're taking a bite out of the
person, you're hurting the person. תרבית tarbis *tarbit* is from the word
ריבוי *ribui*, רוב *rov*, מרבה *marbeh* because you are getting a profit.
Okay, so that's the two sides. From the borrower is being bitten
out of and the lender, the creditor is making a profit. נשך
ותרבית neshech v'tarbis? *Neshech ve-tarbit*. And the
משנה Mishna *Mishnah* though is going to distinguish them and use נשך
neshech *neshech* to describe דאורייתא d'Oraisa ריבית ribis *de-Oraisa ribis* and תרבית
tarbis *tarbit* to describe דרבנן d'Rabanan ריבית ribbis. *de-Rabbanan ribis*. Let's take
a look. איזהו נשך neshech ואיזו תרבית tarbis *Eizehu neshech ve-eizo tarbit*.
איזהו נשך neshech, *Eizehu neshech*? What's נשך neshech *neshech*? המלוה סלע בחמשה
דינרין *Ha-malveh sela be-chamisha dinarin*. Somebody who lends a סלע *sela* which
is worth four דינר dinar, *dinar* and he sells and he and
he lends it for five דינרין *dinarin*. You have to pay back,
you know, you have to pay back more, straight case of interest.
I'm lending you four, you pay me back five. סאתים חטים בשלש
*Sa'atayim chitin be-shalosh* or two סאה *se'ah* of grain. It doesn't it's
not limited to money, it applies to food. Two סאה *se'ah* of
grain and you pay me back three. Why does the משנה Mishna
*Mishnah* make the point of money and grain? Because the פסוקים pesukim
*psukim* also in some פסוקים pesukim *psukim* just say לא תקח מאתו
נשך neshech. ותרבית *lo tikach me-ito neshech ve-tarbit*, don't make a distinction.
But other פסוקים *psukim* say את כספך *es kaspacha* we'll see this
in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* לא תתן לו בנשך ובמרבית לא תתן
אכלך *lo siten lo be-neshech u-be-marbis lo siten ochlecha*. So it uses
in one פסוק pasuk *pasuk* uses the word נשך neshech. *neshech* for
money and מרבית marbis, *marbis* for food. So you might have thought
that's the distinction. So the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* is telling you no
that's not the distinction. Straight case of charging more lending X and
and demanding back X plus Y, you know, more than you lent,
whether money or food we're going to call that נשך neshech *neshech*
and that's going to be basically ריבית Ribbis דאורייתא d'Oraisa *ribis de-Oraisa*.
Okay. ואיזו תרבית tarbit *Ve-eizo tarbit*.
Now what's תרבית tarbis *tarbit*? המרבה בפירות *Ha-marbeh be-feiros* when you wind
up getting more from fruit that you lent or sold. What does
that mean? כיצד *Keitzad*? What's the case? And we'll read this in
the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* but there'll be a whole גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
trying to understand exactly this case. לקח הימנו חטים בדינר זהב הכור
*Lakach heimenu chitin be-dinar zahav ha-kor*. Okay, וכן השער *ve-chein ha-sha'ar*. So
you went over to a farmer and you said and you went
at the time when there was the שער *sha'ar* means that's the
standard market rate. Everybody has just harvested their grain starting to sell
it to the retailers and to you know or to the wholesalers
or whatever and there's a standard market rate. And the standard market
rate is a for one golden דינר dinar, *dinar* you get a
כור kor *kor* of grain, a certain unit of grain. Okay, so
you go to the farmer and you say you give him here's
a golden דינר dinar. *dinar* and I am buying from you a
כור kor *kor* of grain.
And but really but you're going to pay me not now, what
you're going to do is you're going to supply me with grain
over the course of the year from this כור kor *kor*. Okay,
and imagine of course a very large unit. Now later the prices
are going to go up. Now when the first harvest is coming
and people are selling to the wholesalers the prices are low, later...
in the year most likely the prices will be higher, but you're
buying it now to be delivered over the course of the year.
So now that itself you might think could be a type of
a רבית ribbis because when he finally does deliver it, you know,
or some of it, he's actually going to be worth more. So
I gave him a דינר, dinar a golden דינר, dinar and then
I got grain that if you were to figure out the value
of the time that I'm getting it was actually worth more than
a דינר. dinar But actually that's allowed, because since this farmer has
already the grain or we'll see in the גמרא Gemara that it's
the market rate and it's easily accessible and he could buy it
from anybody, so then it's basically like a sale. Okay? Since that
grain can he has it or can easily be bought, so and
then he'll just deliver it later. It's not seen as a loan,
it's seen as a type of a sale or close enough to
a sale that it's not a concern of רבית ribbis even if
it's worth more when it gets delivered. So so far we're good.
Now עמדו חטים בלמד דינרים, Amdu chitin b'lamed dinarim, and now the
grain cost a golden דינר dinar is twenty-five silver, and now that
same amount of grain costs thirty. Okay? So as expected it went
up after time. If he were to just deliver the כור kor
of grain, שלום על ישראל, Shalom al Yisrael, it would be fine.
Okay, but that's not what happened. אמר לו תן לי חטי שאני
רוצה למכרן וליקח בהן יין. Amar lo ten li chittai she'ani rotze
l'mochran v'likach bahen yayin. So now the person who bought the grain
says, okay, give me my grain. I ordered a כור kor of
grain, give it to me now and now I want to sell
it at the higher price and I'm going to use it to
buy wine and now I want to invest in wine. אמר לו
הרי חטיך עשוי עלי בשלושים והרי לך אצלי בהן יין. Amar lo
harei chittecha asui alai b'shloshim v'harei lach etzli bahen yayin. He says,
you know what, look, this כור kor of grain that I owe
you is worth thirty silver דינרים. dinarim. Let's say, let's call it
at thirty דינר dinar. and and I will now promise to give
you thirty silver דינר dinar. worth of wine. But he doesn't have
the wine. So that's a problem. Okay? It sounds like if he
had just said, okay, I'm supposed well we know it's clearly if
he had just said I'm going to deliver to you this כור
of grain even though now it's worth more that would be okay.
It sounds like from the משנה Mishna even if he had said
to you that כור of grain is worth thirty דינר dinar. as
opposed to the twenty-five you know it went up from the twenty-five
I'm going to give you thirty דינר. dinar It sounds like that
would also be okay if he could give him the כור of
grain he could give him the thirty דינר. dinar, The problem is
he can't promise to give him wine that he doesn't have and
that wine when he eventually delivers it might be worth more than
the thirty דינר. dinar. So that seems very complicated. So we will
get to all of that in the גמרא Gemara but somehow it's
a case where you it was sort of a purchase but when
it's delivered it's worth more and therefore it could under some circumstances
be sometimes it's okay but under some circumstances it could be considered
like רבית ribbis because it's worth more when it's delivered. All right,
let's take a look. We'll get to that in a few days.
Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara מדשביק לריבית דאורייתא וקמפרש דרבנן. Mide'shavik l'ribbis d'Oraisa v'kamafaresh d'Rabanan.
So when it got to תרבית tarbis in the in the משנה
Mishna it started clearly talking about some דרבנן d'Rabanan case because דאורייתא
d'Oraisa the only case of רבית דאורייתא ribbis d'Oraisa is I'm lending
you X you pay me back X plus something and that's the
agreement from the beginning. That was a loan and the agreement was
to pay back more than you got. And clearly whatever the second
case is in the משנה Mishna it's some דרבנן d'Rabanan problem. So
from the fact that the משנה Mishna when it got to the
word רבית ribbis abandoned trying to explain a דאורייתא d'Oraisa category and
went to a דרבנן d'Rabanan category מכלל דאורייתא דנשך ותרבית חדא מילתא
היא. michlal d'Oraisa d'neshech v'tarbis chada milsa hi. From this we can
infer that when the תורה Torah says נשך neshech ותרבית they're not
talking about different things meaning the משנה Mishna could have said what's
נשך neshech ותרבית? Because two words are used in the תורה Torah
and it could have explained נשך neshech, means one type of תורה
Torah category. תרבית tarbit? means another type of תורה Torah category. That's
what we would have expected the משנה Mishna to do. But it
didn't do that. What it did was it went ahead and it
described תרבית tarbis as some דרבנן category which makes it sound like
in the תורה Torah there are no two categories. There's only one
תורה Torah category. And we the רבנים Rabbanim are going to use
the word תרבית tarbis to describe דרבנן רבית. d'Rabanan ribbis. But the
fact that the משנה did not bother to explain two different דאורייתא
categories sounds like the משנה's assumption is that דאורייתא it's all the
same. מכלל דנשך ותרבית חדא מילתא היא. Michlal d'neshech v'tarbis chada milsa
hi. So the גמרא Gemara says והקרא כתיב נשך כסף ריבית אוכל.
V'ha kraya ksiv neshech kesef ribbis ochel.
But why why is the משנה assuming that? The תורה Torah? speaks
about נשך neshech by money and רבית ribbis. by food. So why
shouldn't we say that those are two different לאוין lavin and they
might be very similar but one applies to money and one applies
to food? What made the משנה assume that it's all one category
in the תורה? Torah
So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברא דאיכא נשך בלא תרבית ותרבית בלא
נשך? V'tisabra de'ika neshech belo tarbis v'tarbis belo neshech? So now... So
the גמרא Gemara says okay, but the גמרא's Gemara also assuming that
it's not just arbitrarily that נשך neshech would apply to כסף, kesef,
to money, is just a different word that they're, one word applies
to money and one word applies to food. The גמרא's Gemara assuming
that the word נשך neshech, and תרבית tarbis refer to different aspects
of רבית. That נשך neshech, is that the borrower is being taken
a bite out of him, is being, is losing, and תרבית tarbis,
suggests that the lender is getting a profit. So when the גמרא
Gemara is saying why didn't we look at the פסוקים and say
נשך neshech? is by money and תרבית tarbis. is by food, which
is how the פסוקים speak, what it means is not just to
arbitrarily say it's the exact same thing but one applies to money
and one applies to food. Why don't we say that by money
the prohibition is hurting the borrower and by food the prohibition is
making a profit off of the money? All right, so why didn't
we say these words mean different things and one applies to money
and one applies to food? So to that the גמרא's Gemara, going
to respond back you can't have one without the other, so they
have to, they always come together. Okay, so let's take a look.
ותסברא דאיכא נשך בלא תרבית ותרבית בלא נשך? v'tisbarah d'ika neshech blo
tarbis v'tarbis blo neshech? So does that make sense that you could
have נשך neshech, without תרבית tarbis? and תרבית without נשך, neshech that
you could speak about an איסור issur of one without the איסור
issur of the other? What would you think that would be a
case of something like that? So let's take a look at how
you might imagine what that would look like, one without the other.
נשך בלא תרבית היכי דמי? neshech blo tarbis hechi dami? What would
that look like? אי דאוזפי מאה במאה ועשרין. ei d'ozfei mea b'mea
v'esrim. So you lent him a hundred with the agreement he'd pay
back a hundred and twenty. Right? And that's נשך כסף. neshech kesef.
All right. So מעיקרא קיימי מאה בדנקא ולבסוף קיימי מאה ועשרין בדנקא.
mei'ikara kamei mea b'danka ul'basof kamei mea v'esrim b'danka.
Now
originally when you lent it to him a hundred פרוטות prutos went
for a sixth, a sixth of a דינר which is a מעה.
ma'ah. Okay, מעה ma'ah is a hundred פרוטות. prutos. So when you
lent him the hundred you said I'm going to lend you a
hundred you pay back a hundred and twenty. Now when at the
time of the lending the hundred was worth one מעה. ma'ah. Right?
We don't have where our money changes relative to the different coinage
but they did in the גמרא because it was different precious metals.
Okay, so let's say when you lent him it was a hundred
for one, a hundred pennies was worth a dollar, we'll just call
it that. מעיקרא קיימי מאה בדנקא ולבסוף mei'ikara kamei mea b'danka ul'basof
now when he pays you back the hundred and twenty קיימי מאה
ועשרין בדנקא kamei mea v'esrim b'danka now a hundred and twenty pennies
is a dollar. Okay. So what's happening? So you might think נשך
איכא, neshech ika, okay that is נשך neshech a bite you took
a bite out of him, right? דקגבי ליה דקנכית ליה d'kagavi lei
d'kanachis lei
because he's losing money דקשקיל מיניה מידי דלא יהב, d'kashakul minei midi
d'lo yahav, okay
that you are taking from him something that you didn't give him.
He received a hundred, he's giving back a hundred and twenty, so
he was hurt. That's נשך. Why isn't it תרבית? ותרבית ליכא, v'tarbis
leka, but you the lender even though you got a hundred and
twenty, when you got it back, so you didn't get any profit.
דלית ליה ריוחא דדנקא אוזיף ודנקא קשקיל מיניה. d'leis lei rivcha d'danka
ozif v'danka kashakul minei.
When you lent it to him it was worth a dollar and
when you got back a hundred and twenty it was worth a
dollar. So that's a case where you when you got back the
money it had the same buying power as when you lent it,
you didn't get any profit, but he, he gave back more, he
was bitten out of because he gave back more than he took.
So the גמרא says okay, but like no. סוף סוף אי בתר
מעיקרא אזלת הוי נשך והוי תרבית אי בתר סוף אזלת לא נשך
איכא ולא תרבית איכא. sof sof ei basar mei'ikara azlat havoi neshech
v'havai tarbis ei basar basof azlat lo neshech hava v'lo tarbis ika.
Why would you be looking at different times when you're focusing on
the borrower and when you're focusing on the lender? If you focus
on originally, so
originally it was worth a hundred, he'll say that again, אי
בתר מעיקרא אזלת הוי נשך והוי תרבית. ei basar mei'ikara azlat havoi
neshech v'havai tarbis. So yes, you gave, so if you look at
the original value you gave him a hundred and he gave up
a hundred and twenty, so he gave more than he took, so
he was bitten out of. But you also as the lender got
more than you gave, you got back a hundred and twenty, you
only gave a hundred. So if you're focusing on the value at
the time of the
loan then the borrower got a bite out of him and the
lender got more than he gave.
אי בתר סוף אזלת, ei basar basof azlat, if you're looking at
the value when it was paid, so לא נשך איכא, lo neshech
ika, then the borrower didn't have a bite taken from him. He
got something that at the time he got it it had a
certain buying power and now when he's paying it back he's paying
back something of an equal buying power, so that's not a bite
out of him based on the value right now. ולא תרבית איכא,
v'lo tarbis ika, and similarly the lender. lender is not getting a
profit because it has equal buying power. So you can't have one
without the other. You know, yes it could be different if you
look at the time of lending and the time of the borrowing,
but that's not going to be a difference—I mean the time of
the lending and the time of the repayment—but it's not going to
be a difference between the lender and between the lender and the
borrower, between the תרבית and the נשך. So you can't have one
without the other.
Similarly, וזו תרבית בלא נשך היכי דמי. v'zu tarbis b'lo neshech heichi
dami. What's the case about תרבית profit that you could imagine, you
know, you would say תרבית is only by food, you know, ובמרבית
לא תיתן אכלך, u'v'marbis lo siten achlecha,
so by food the focus is on making a profit. Says okay,
but how are you going to have that without the other guy
suffering a loss? וזו תרבית בלא נשך היכי דמי. v'zu tarbis b'lo
neshech heichi dami. אי דאוזיף מאה במאה ei d'ozif me'ah b'me'ah מעיקרא
קיימי מאה בדנקא. me'ikara kaimei me'ah b'danka. So let's say you lent
him 100 pennies and you said he's going to have to pay
you back 100 pennies. That sounds nice for him, no, okay. But
מעיקרא קיימי מאה בדנקא, me'ikara kaimei me'ah b'danka, originally that 100 pennies
was worth a sixth of a דינר, a מעה, ma'ah, a dollar.
ולבסוף, u'l'vasof, and when it came time to pay back, מאה בחומשא,
me'ah b'chumsha, it was worth a fifth of a דינר. So it
was actually now, you know, those 100 pennies were worth a dollar
and a quarter.
So in that case, you know, you would say, you know, you
had a... where was I?
You, the lender, got תרבית, you got profit, because when you got
it back it had more buying power. It had a dollar and
a quarter buying power. But he wasn't... didn't get a bite taken
out of him because he got 100 pennies and he paid back
100 pennies. But the גמרא says no, again, it's not a difference
between profit versus bite, between lender versus borrower. It's a difference between
which time are you focusing on. So the... so אי בתר מעיקרא
אזלת ei basar me'ikara azlas לא נשך ולא תרבית איכא. lo neshech
v'lo tarbis ika.
If you go by originally, he gave him 100 and he got
back 100. And if you go by its buying power that was
at that time, this guy didn't profit and that guy didn't get
a bite taken out of him. אי בתר לבסוף אזלת ei basar
l'vasof azlas הרי נשך והרי תרבית. harei neshech v'harei tarbis.
This guy had to pay back something of a buying power of
a dollar and a quarter, so he had a bite taken out
of him, and the other guy got back something with higher buying
power, so he got profit. So there's no way, says the גמרא,
you can separate נשך and תרבית.
So it's true that one appears in the תורה Torah by food
and one appears by money, but the words, even though they have
different connotations, cannot refer to different איסורים issurim because they always
come—one is always the flip side of the other. Okay? And that's
why we are not inclined to say that by money it's a
problem of a bite and by food it's a problem of a
profit. And we really are just going to combine the two.
So... אלא אמר רבא אי אתה מוצא לא נשך בלא תרבית ולא
תרבית בלא נשך. ella amar Rava i ata motza lo neshech b'lo
tarbis v'lo tarbis b'lo neshech. So you don't have one without the
other, and therefore they're not separate איסורים. issurim. ולמה חלקן הכתוב אלא
לעבור עליו בשני לאווין. v'lama chelkan haksav ella la'avor alav b'shnei lavin.
And why did it call it נשך and תרבית? To tell you
that when you do it, you transgress both. You transgress for making
a profit that you shouldn't have made and for taking a bite
out of the person that you shouldn't have taken. Okay? But really,
there aren't... we're not going to... we're not going to say arbitrarily
one type of איסור issur for money and one type of איסור
issur for food. If we can't conceptually explain them as different איסורים,
issurim, then we're going to say they're basically the same איסור issur
and they apply equally to money and to food. Okay? And now
we're actually going to see that a פסוק, pasuk even though one
פסוק pasuk separates them with money and food, another פסוק pasuk does
not and that again reinforces the idea that we're going to treat
it all as one. תנו רבנן את כספך לא תתן לו בנשך
ובמרבית לא תתן אכלך אין לי אלא נשך בכסף וריבית באוכל. tanu
rabanan es kaspecha lo siten lo b'neshech u'v'marbis lo siten achlecha ein
li ella neshech b'chesef v'ribis b'ochel. So that's the פסוק pasuk I
was referring to.
נשך by money and ריבית ribbis by food. נשך באוכל מנין? neshech
b'ochel minayin? How do you know that even נשך, that prohibition applies
by food as well? תלמוד לומר נשך אוכל. talmud lomar neshech ochel.
So that's a פסוק pasuk in דברים, Devarim, not in ויקרא: Vayikra:
נשך כסף נשך אוכל. neshech kesef neshech ochel.
So the פסוק pasuk... actually does explicitly say נשך both by money
and by food. Good. So that's נשך applies to both. נשך אוכל.
neshech ochel. ריבית בכסף מנין? ribis b'chesef minayin? How do you know
מרבית, that prohibition, even if it's the same as נשך, but if
you want to get the guy twice, how do you know that
prohibition applies by money? Never says it in the תורה Torah by
money. תלמוד לומר נשך כסף נשך כסף. talmud lomar neshech kesef neshech
kesef.
Because again this פסוק pasuk says נשך כסף נשך אוכל. neshech kesef
neshech ochel. אם אינו ענין לנשך כסף שהרי כבר נאמר לא תשיך
לאחיך. im eino inyan l'neshech kesef sheharei kvar ne'emar lo sashich l'achicha.
Okay, if you don't need this פסוק pasuk by... to say it
by money because we already know another פסוק... pasuk, the פסוק already
says you can't do נשך, didn't have to say again נשך כסף.
neshech kesef. And even the earlier פסוק in ויקרא Vayikra already explicitly
stated את כספך לא תתן לו בנשך. es kaspecha lo siten lo
b'neshech. So what's the repetition of נשך? אתני ענין לריבית כסף. Atnei
inyan l'ribbis kesef. Okay, that's coming to teach you that it's not
only נשך, it's also ריבית. ribbis, So we know the word נשך
is applied in the תורה Torah both to money and to food.
ריבית ribbis, in the תורה is only applied to food, but because
there's an extra פסוק, we say that the ריבית ribbis. prohibition applies
to money as well. And we're also really saying there's no real
difference; they describe different aspects of ריבית, but whether you lend money
or food with ריבית, you transgress both the לאו lav of נשך
and the לאו lav of ריבית. Okay, we will end here for
now and we will finish up this ברייתא braisa tomorrow.